<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Wynand Booysen - Python</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/python.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-10-08T18:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>FitBit Presence Detection</title><link href="/fitbit-presence-detection.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-10-08T18:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-10-08T18:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Wynand Booysen</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-10-08:/fitbit-presence-detection.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;FitBit Presence Detection&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Show with the launch of the FitBit Alta and the new FitBit Flex 2 the prices of the FitBit Flex was bound to go down.  So I picked up a FitBit Flex for just R800.  So why did I get one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well I try and keep fit and tracking your activity helps you stay motivated.  But mainly I wanted to check the sleep monitoring function and have another Bluetooth device to be possibly used for presence detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the FitBit Flex uses a Nordic Semiconductor nRF8001 chip - which is for Bluetooth 4.0 LE connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also comes with a USB dongle that uses Texas Instruments CC2540F128 Bluetooth LE SoC to sync the Flex's data via a computer instead of the phone app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So since the Flex is a Bluetooth device it should have unique hardware address (MAC)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galileo is a Python utility by Benoit Allard that allows communication with the Bluetooth based FitBit devices and sync to FitBit website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using Galileo you can scan for FitBit devices to sync their data.  It will list all devices along with their MAC addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple bash script and we can grep for the specific unit's MAC address and execute something when the device is present.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="fitbit"></category><category term="Bluetooth"></category></entry><entry><title>Moving to Pelican</title><link href="/moving-to-pelican.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-07-21T17:05:00+02:00</published><updated>2016-07-21T17:05:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Wynand Booysen</name></author><id>tag:None,2016-07-21:/moving-to-pelican.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Moving to Pelican&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is my first post after switching to Pelican.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that running a Virtual Private Server just to host WordPress was overkill, so I started looking at static site generators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately ended up going with Pelican - Python based, mature and feature rich enough for what I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I only need to write more often :-)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="pelican"></category><category term="publishing"></category></entry></feed>